8

Beneath the Surface

These dramatic encounters with demons had opened a window onto a strange, new spiritual realm. Passages in the gospels describing demonic manifestations were no longer records from an alien culture or the remote past. They had suddenly come alive. I had seen in my own experience that these accounts were just as relevant in twentieth-century United States as in first-century Israel.

Years later, while on vacation, I had an experience that brought back memories of these first confrontations with demons. When I went snorkelling for the first time and looked under the surface of the water, I was confronted with a new world. Unfamiliar creatures in dazzling colours moved to and fro against a background of plants and coral unlike anything I had ever seen on dry land. Just imagine, I said to myself. This other world has been close to me nearly all my life and I was scarcely aware of its existence! Yet all I had to do was put on a snorkel and look down into the water!

It seems to me that we in our “advanced” Western civilisation have been like swimmers without snorkels. Our humanistic, anti-supernatural view of the universe has kept us from recognising the reality of a demonic realm that has never been far from us. In parts of the world like Africa or Asia, people have always been conscious of demons and can describe many tangible demonstrations of their intrusion into human affairs.

In the West, too, demons exercise a continuous and powerful influence on our lives, but our humanistic prejudice has blinded us to the evidence. In fact, our refusal to acknowledge the evidence makes it easier for demons to operate undetected. We tend to cloak their activity with high-sounding psychological or psychiatric terminology – yet the “cures” we claim are often disappointing.

The “snorkel” we need is a return to the spiritual perspective of the New Testament. Jesus and His apostles openly recognised the reality of demons and demonstrated how to deal with them. The cures they achieved were often dramatic and always effective.

Now, as I studied the gospel accounts in the light of my new experiences, my previous ministry began to seem superficial. I took to heart the Lord’s assessment of the prophets of Israel in Jeremiah’s day: “They have also healed the hurt of My people slightly, saying, ‘Peace, peace!’ when there is no peace” (Jeremiah 6:14).

Frequently I had failed to discern the demonic nature of the problems in people I had counselled. I had dealt with only superficial behavioural manifestations. As a result, some of the apparent victories were incomplete or short-lived. All too often there was no real spiritual progress. We had been like Israel at Mount Sinai, going around the same mountain again and again instead of setting out on the road toward our God-given destination.

The apostle Paul said of his ministry, “I do not fight like a man beating the air” (1 Corinthians 9:26, niv). I saw that I had at times been an unskilful boxer, lashing out with my fists but not landing blows on my opponent’s body. My preaching and prayers had failed to come to grips with the demons tormenting and crippling those to whom I ministered.

But now that began to change. In a few, brief weeks, God moved my ministry into a new dimension. As desperate people came to me almost every day, I tried to follow the pattern of Jesus, and I evaluated my progress against the record of the New Testament.

When Jesus dealt with demons, for instance, they apparently asked him not to do certain things, such as sending them “out into the abyss” (Luke 8:31), but there is no record that they ever defied or refused to obey Him. In my first encounters, on the other hand, some of the demons had, for a time, openly defied me. In the case of Esther, I believe they were hoping to frighten me, so I would not press my attack against them.

I recognised that my authority over them was derived from Jesus, but manifestly it was not on the same level as His. I learned, however, that when I quoted Scripture persistently, declaring His victory and invoking His name, the demons were brought into subjection.

One particular theological question arose from my experiences with Esther, Rose and Sharon: How far is it wise, or right, to exchange words with demons? The clearest pattern in the ministry of Jesus is recorded in Luke 8:27-33:

When Jesus stepped ashore, he was met by a demon-possessed [demonized] man from the town. For a long time this man had not worn clothes or lived in a house, but had lived in the tombs. When he saw Jesus, he cried out and fell at his feet, shouting at the top of his voice, “What do you want with me, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I beg you, don’t torture me!” For Jesus had commanded the evil spirit to come out of the man. Many times it had seized him, and though he was chained hand and foot and kept under guard, he had broken his chains and had been driven by the demon into solitary places.

Jesus asked him, “What is your name?”

“Legion,” he replied, because many demons had gone into him. And they begged him repeatedly not to order them to go into the Abyss.

A large herd of pigs was feeding there on the hillside. The demons begged Jesus to let them go into them, and he gave them permission. When the demons came out of the man, they went into the pigs, and the herd rushed down the steep bank into the lake and was drowned.

(niv)

Luke’s record makes certain points clear.

Jesus began by commanding the demon to come out of the man. Then the man – or the demon in the man – not only spoke but shouted at Jesus (see verse 28).

Jesus then asked the demon, “What is your name?” (verse 30). The demon answered, “Legion.” A legion normally numbered between 4,200 and 6,000 soldiers. Clearly there were many demons in the man.

Then the demons “begged him repeatedly” not to order them into the Abyss (verse 31). Probably many different demons were speaking out of the man and had a lot to say! Jesus apparently made no attempt to prevent them speaking.

Eventually the demons sought to strike a bargain – “If we have to go out, please let us go into the pigs” – and Jesus gave them permission (see verse 32).

When the demons entered the pigs, all two thousand of them (see Mark 5:13) stampeded into the lake and were drowned (see verse 33). Isn’t it amazing that one man could contain enough demons to send two thousand pigs to their death in the lake?

Meditating on this account, I arrived at two conclusions. First, it is scriptural – and sometimes necessary – to ask a demon, “What is your name?” Second, if demons answer back, it is necessary to deal with their answers, until they are forced to acknowledge the authority of Christ and to come out of their victim.

Since then I have learned that getting to know the name of a demon provides a “handle” to bring it into subjection. We might compare it to getting to know the name of a dog threatening to attack us. Calling the dog by its name in an authoritative tone of voice can be the first step in bringing it into subjection.

I wondered why Jesus allowed those demons to go into the pigs. Perhaps because it was an alternative they were willing to accept. If they had been forced to go out of the man without being allowed to enter alternative victims, they might have put up such a struggle that the man would not have been able to survive the pressure.

It is important to bear in mind that all Jesus said and did was directed toward one practical end: to get the demons out of the man. This incident cannot be used to justify conversing with demons for any other purpose.

In particular, I came to understand that it is altogether wrong and extremely dangerous to seek any kind of special revelation from demons. God has given us His Holy Spirit as our all-sufficient Teacher and Revelator. The Holy Spirit is the Spirit of truth, whereas Satan is the father of lies. To seek revelation from some satanic source, therefore, is to dishonour the Holy Spirit and to expose ourselves to deception.1

In those first few weeks God gave me deep compassion for those who are bound by demons. I began to look below the surface of problems that appeared purely physical or psychological, and to identify the underlying demonic forces at work. It was exciting to be able to help people whose needs I could never previously have understood. God began to put within me a burning indignation that so many of His people are still in bondage to demons.

After Jesus released a woman who had been bent double for eighteen years with a spirit of infirmity, the religious leaders challenged Him because He was not following their rules for observing the Sabbath. He responded indignantly, “Ought not this woman, being a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan has bound – think of it – for eighteen years, be loosed from this bond on the Sabbath?” (Luke 13:16).

“Amen, Lord!” I reply. “She ought to be loosed! And so ought thousands of others of Your people who are bound and tormented by demons.”

1. In the 1970s a group of ministers who had experience dealing with demons began to hold lengthy conversations with them, seeking to obtain special understanding about things in the spiritual realm. In the end this proved disastrous. The group went into serious doctrinal error and some of them died prematurely.

9

Lessons from an Expanding Ministry

While Lydia and I were busy ministering to people in our home, our congregation was busy, too, discussing what had happened to Sharon, our pianist. Some of our people were jubilant over the victory that had been won. Others were fearful and confused. So I announced that I would give some systematic teaching on this topic at our midweek Bible study.

About one hundred people gathered. I led them objectively through the New Testament references to demons, taking care to point out how to recognise and deal with them. But as I prepared to close the Bible study with a standard pastoral prayer of dismissal, the people began to protest.

“You can’t stop now!” they said. “We need help.”

“How many people need help?” I asked. “Put up your hands.”

When about fifty people raised their hands, I was faced with a crisis. I remembered my intense struggles in ministering to one individual at a time. How could I possibly cope with fifty?

At that moment I received a flash of inspiration. I recalled occasions when I had preached a message of salvation and ten or twenty people had come forward to repent. Never for a moment had I imagined that it was my responsibility to save them. As I had led them in a prayer, each one made personal contact with the only One who could save him or her – Jesus Christ, the Saviour. Over the years I had seen hundreds of people receive salvation by this simple procedure.

The same Christ who is the only Saviour, I reasoned, is the only Deliverer. Only Jesus can break the power of demonic bondage in people’s lives and set them free. So I should be able to introduce them to the Deliverer in just the same way.

I asked those who had raised their hands to come to the front, telling the others to stay and pray quietly in their seats. Then I explained to those wanting deliverance that they needed to make direct personal contact with Christ, and I outlined four simple conditions they needed to meet:

Be sure you have repented – that is, turned away from every form of sin
Look only to Jesus; He alone is the Deliverer
Base your appeal solely on what Jesus did for you through His death on the cross, not on any “good works” of your own
Be sure that, by an act of your will, you have forgiven every person who ever harmed or wronged you

Finally I reminded them of the promise through which I myself had received deliverance from the demon of depression: “Whoever calls on the name of the Lord shall be saved” (Joel 2:32). I also quoted the words of Jesus: “In my name you shall expel demons” (Mark 16:17, Weymouth). And I added, “In the name of Jesus you have the authority to expel them from yourselves.”

I led them in a simple, step-by-step prayer covering the conditions they needed to meet, and closed with, “And now, Lord Jesus, I renounce any evil spirit that has gained any control over me, and I claim Your promise of deliverance. In Your name, Lord Jesus.” Then I prayed a collective prayer for all of them, as they began to receive deliverance.

The next fifteen minutes were lively – screaming, sobbing, coughing, shaking. Some fell to the floor, while others gave no outward indication that anything was taking place inside them.

When things quieted down, I asked how many of them felt they had received the deliverance they had prayed for. About 75 percent raised their hands. The remaining 25 percent needed further, individual ministry. I dismissed the people whose needs had been met, and Lydia and I did our best to help those who remained behind. In most cases we simply stood with them, encouraging them to press through to deliverance for themselves and to use the name of Jesus against their enemy. We also gave them appropriate Scriptures to quote.

In some cases it became clear that they had not fulfilled all the conditions I had outlined. The hindrance we needed to emphasise most, as it turned out, was failure to forgive those who had harmed or wronged them.

Out of this experience I learned one vitally important principle: The most important issue was not whether I had the necessary authority, but whether the people seeking deliverance had met God’s conditions for receiving it. The promise of Jesus to His disciples has never varied: “Behold, I give you the authority . . . over all the power of the enemy, and nothing shall by any means hurt you” (Luke 10:19). The variable factor in each situation is the response of those to whom we minister. When people meet the scriptural requirements, deliverance follows.

Full deliverance, however, may not be immediate but progressive, as people come to understand the various areas of their lives that have been affected by demonic influence. Often there looms in the background the dark shadow of a generational curse or a curse from occult sources. (I deal with this in my book Blessing or Curse: You Can Choose! and will say more about it in chapter 21.)

Controversy

From that first experience I came to see that the ministry of deliverance is not primarily a test of my personal authority. It is a means of helping people in desperate need. Since then I have continually placed my main emphasis on explaining God’s conditions and urging people to make the right response.

That midweek Bible study was a turning point in my ministry. When I discovered that the majority of people could receive their deliverance collectively, after proper instruction, I was no longer restricted to one-on-one deliverance. In fact, I found that the combined faith of one hundred people all gathered for the same purpose is usually greater than the faith of a single individual.

Once I grasped this principle, the Lord began to open the way for me to apply it on a much wider scale. In 1964 I finally resigned my pastorate and moved out in faith as an itinerant Bible teacher, combining the ministries of teaching and deliverance.

The Lord made it clear to me at the outset that He did not want me to become a “specialist” in deliverance. I understood that delivering people from demons is an integral part of the message of the Gospel, not some unusual extra reserved for “experts.” My example was Jesus, who “travelled throughout Galilee, preaching in their synagogues and driving out demons” (Mark 1:39, niv). Apparently Jesus was always ready to drive out demons when He preached. If He had not done so, He would have failed to meet the needs of some of the people, and His ministry would have been incomplete.

As the Lord began to open one door after another before me, my name became known to various sectors of the Body of Christ in the U.S. Some people objected vehemently to the manifestations that frequently accompanied the ministry of deliverance, but others sent urgent messages asking for my help. The cries for help outnumbered the criticisms.

One early experience stands out in my memory. In 1965 I was asked to be the Bible teacher at a large, international Full Gospel convention in the Conrad Hilton Hotel in Chicago. One day I gave a Bible study to about six hundred people on deliverance from demons. When I asked at the end how many felt they might need deliverance, at least two hundred people put up their hands. Looking at them, I breathed a prayer of thanks to God for teaching me the principles of collective prayer for deliverance!

When the people came forward, I gave them the same basic instruction on meeting God’s conditions that had proved effective with smaller groups. Then I led them in a step-by-step prayer, just as in other such meetings. Finally I told them to cry out to the Lord individually for deliverance, while I prayed a collective prayer for them all.

The scene that followed was somewhat chaotic. Two or three fell to the floor and lay writhing and struggling as the demons came out. Some women were screaming as demons came out of them. Still others rushed out in a panic and went up to their hotel rooms, declaring they would not come back so long as I was preaching.

This meeting provoked a good deal of adverse criticism. Yet in subsequent years I often met people from all over the U.S. who told me, “I got delivered in that service in the Conrad Hilton Hotel in 1965.”

Some people opposed my ministry of deliverance on the basis that I did not do it as effectively as Jesus. They would quote Matthew 8:16: “He cast out the spirits with a word, and healed all who were sick” – implying there were no noisy or disorderly disturbances when Jesus ministered. But, as I said in chapter 3, that is not correct. Other passages in that gospel describe incidents that were both noisy and disorderly.

Furthermore, Matthew records that Jesus not only expelled demons but also “healed all who were sick.” Like many other preachers, I had prayed for the sick and had not seen them all healed. Yet I did not recall anyone ever attacking me for not ministering to the sick as effectively as Jesus did. Why, then, should people focus only on the area of dealing with demons?

Again, I knew that I did not teach as well as Jesus, yet no one had ever criticised me for this or suggested it as a reason I should stop teaching. Furthermore, some of the very people who criticised my deliverance meetings were themselves Bible teachers. I was sure they, too, would acknowledge that they did not teach as well as Jesus. Yet it did not seem to occur to them that they should give up teaching. So, again, why was criticism focused on this ministry of deliverance?

I suggest two main reasons. First, because Satan jealously guards the secrets of his demonic kingdom. Over the centuries he has built up in the minds of Christians a barrier of fear and superstitious ignorance keeping us from acknowledging either the truths of Scripture or the facts of experience.

The second reason is that the professing Christian Church has established a pattern of behaviour considered “appropriate” for the house of God. Too often this leaves no room for the messy facts of human sin and demonic oppression. Some churchgoers are offended by the noisy and disorderly manifestations that sometimes accompany the driving out of demons. Dignity takes precedence over deliverance.

I looked again at the ministry of Jesus and discovered various instances in which a demon or demons screamed and shouted at Him; interrupted His preaching; convulsed people when they came out, leaving them apparently dead; caused a person to wallow on the ground foaming at the mouth; and stampeded a herd of two thousand pigs into a lake. Yet Jesus was never disturbed, nor did He suppress these manifestations. He simply dealt with them as part of His total ministry to suffering humanity.

Gradually I came to see that there are three possible sources of such manifestations: the Holy Spirit, evil spirits or unruly human flesh. To each we need to respond appropriately. If certain manifestations are from the Holy Spirit, we need to acknowledge Him and flow with Him. If they issue from an evil spirit, we need to take a stand against it and expel it. If they come from unruly human flesh, we need to exercise discipline and bring it under control.

The scriptural solution, however, is not to exercise such rigid control over every meeting that no disorderly manifestations are ever permitted. This would go far beyond the pattern set by Jesus. Furthermore, it overlooks the fact that in the ministry of Jesus it was the anointing of the Holy Spirit that forced the demons to manifest themselves. A similar anointing today will produce similar results.

If demons never manifest themselves, then there is no opportunity to expel them. They remain below the surface in people’s lives, free to continue their harmful and destructive activities. Given their choice, no doubt demons would rather be “controlled” than expelled. At the same time, I recognise that I was slow sometimes to identify the source of certain manifestations. I tolerated fleshly demonstrations, attributing these to a spiritual source and not dealing appropriately with them. (Over the years, I trust, I have become more sensitive to these issues.)

But not all the criticisms I received were hostile. Some of my friends said to me, “Derek, it’s all right to cast out demons, but you don’t have to do it in public where it disturbs people.” This seemed reasonable to me, but I felt that before changing my methods, I ought to further study the ministry of Jesus and see whether He normally dealt with demons in private.

To my surprise, I found in the gospels that there was nothing Jesus did more regularly and consistently in public than drive out demons. I could not find a single instance in which He took a person aside in private for this purpose. This aspect of His ministry excited more public attention than any other. Apparently He was not concerned that those who needed deliverance might be deterred by embarrassment. I decided I would not try to improve on the methods of Jesus!

Other Lessons I Learned

The deepest and most enduring effect in my own life was the new light deliverance cast upon the cross. I discovered in experience that our authority over demons is derived solely from the victory Jesus won for us by His shed blood, His death and His victorious resurrection.

Satan’s primary weapon against the whole human race is guilt. This is why he is “the accuser of [the] brethren” (Revelation 12:10). He reminds God continually that we are all guilty of transgressing God’s righteous law. Hence he contends that we have no claim on God’s mercy but are justly subject to God’s judgement.

But Jesus, by His atoning death on our behalf, “wiped out the handwriting of [legal] requirements that was against us” and “disarmed [the satanic] principalities and powers” (Colossians 2:14-15) by taking from them their primary weapon against us: guilt. As a result, we are now “justified” and “have peace with God” (Romans 5:1). To be justified means to be made righteous with Christ’s righteousness, which retains no record of sin, nothing of which to be guilty. In effect, each of us has been on trial in the court of heaven, and the verdict has been handed down: not guilty! On this basis – and this basis only – we have the right to exercise the authority Jesus has given us over demons.

Through many personal encounters with demons, I have learned that they are not impressed by religious terminology. They scorn denominational labels or ecclesiastical status. But when we use the name of Jesus and boldly affirm the words of Scripture that declare His victory won on the cross – and the unchallengeable righteousness we have received from Him by faith – then their arrogance and viciousness melt away. They begin to act like the contemptible creatures they truly are, and we witness a fulfilment of Revelation 12:11: “[The believers] overcame him [Satan] by the blood of the Lamb and by the word of their testimony.”

On several occasions I have seen a demon manifest fear in the trembling of the body of its victim. This is why James said that “the demons believe – and tremble!” (James 2:19). At other times a demon forces its victim to cover his ears with his hands to avoid hearing the bold proclamation of Jesus’ victory on the cross, which is the only and all-sufficient basis of deliverance, but is torment to demons.

Early in this ministry God impressed me with another truth: the importance of repentance. People who have been taken over by a demon and who then commit some sinful act may say, “I’m not responsible. A demon made me do it! I couldn’t help myself.” By this they imply that they are not guilty and do not therefore need to repent.

But in Acts 17:30 Paul told the men of Athens, “God . . . commands all men everywhere to repent.” The phrase all men everywhere leaves out no person and no place. Every human being without exception is required by God to repent.

The universal reason we all need to repent is that we have all yielded to the rebellious nature we have each inherited from Adam. We are rebels at war with God. We cannot make peace with Him until we lay down our rebellion – that is, until we repent. That is the true nature of repentance: to lay down our rebellion. This is not primarily an emotion; it is an act of the will.

But beyond our universal responsibility for rebellion, each one of us has added our own individual acts of sin and self-will. Sometimes a series of such wrong choices and acts actually brings people to the point that they are no longer able to resist demonic pressure to commit certain sinful acts. They are literally compelled. Nevertheless, they are still responsible for all the wrong things that brought them to that state of powerlessness in the face of evil. Therefore, they still need to repent.

There are, I discovered, two main barriers to deliverance: failure to repent and failure to forgive others and lay down resentment. Once people met these two requirements, I discovered that I had the authority, delegated by Jesus, to drive the demons out of them. But I had to determine the boundaries of my authority.

I had heard, for example, about people who, after they drove demons out, “cast them into the pit.” Was this scriptural? I could find no incident in the New Testament where Jesus cast demons into the pit. In dealing with the man from Gadara (see Matthew 8:28-32), Jesus did accede to the demons’ plea and allow them to go into the herd of pigs. But He did not go beyond that. Previously the demons had asked Jesus, “Have You come here to torment us before the time?” (verse 29). Apparently the demons already knew there was a set time in God’s eternal programme for them to undergo their final punishment, but until that time, they would be permitted to continue their present activities. Accordingly Jesus stayed within the boundaries set by His Father.

International Ministry

As I declared the truths God was teaching me about deliverance, tape recordings of my teachings began to circulate in the U.S. and in other nations. In 1967 I received an invitation to New Zealand, where I conducted my first public deliverance service outside the U.S. In subsequent visits to New Zealand, I have met Christians still talking about that service, and even some who received deliverance there. Since then I have conducted public deliverance services in more than twenty other nations.

One of the most memorable was in 1984 in a remote, rural area in the northwest corner of Zambia in Central Africa. About seven thousand African men and women gathered for a teaching convention at which I was the main speaker. The “auditorium” was a large, natural amphitheatre about the size of an American football field, sloping gently downward toward the speaker’s platform. The underbrush had been cleared away, but trees had been left standing to provide shade. It was like an open-air cathedral with the sunlight streaming through the branches. The people all sat on the ground – men, women, old, young, mothers with babies and small children – completely filling the area.

I had been asked to teach for five days. I saw this as a wonderful opportunity to take the people stage by stage through the redemptive plan of God – out of the slavery of sin and Satan “into the glorious liberty of the children of God” (Romans 8:21).

My first message was on the one, all-sufficient sacrifice that meets the need of all ages and all races: the cross. When I called for those who needed to repent, many responded and received salvation.

Then I taught them how to pass from curse to blessing. I explained that, on the cross, Jesus “[became] a curse for us” so that we might inherit “the blessing of Abraham,” whom God blessed in all things (Galatians 3:13-14). Then I led these Africans – who are very conscious of the reality of curses and fear them greatly – in a prayer of release, in which nearly all participated. (Again, I will say more about this in chapter 21.)

At the end of my message, a well-dressed man came up to me, threw himself on the ground and rolled in the dust at my feet. “Thank you, thank you, thank you!” he said. “All my life I have never known a day without pain. Today, for the first time, I am free from all pain.”

On the third day I taught them how to recognise the activity of demons and to be delivered from them. At the end I led them in a collective prayer of deliverance.

The scene that followed was, to say the least, dramatic. The Africans in that area, keen hunters of animals, had been taught by witch doctors that, in order to be successful, they must open themselves up to the “spirit” of the particular animal (such as a lion, elephant or boar) that they intended to hunt. Unfortunately, often their wives were also taken over by similar spirits.

When we prayed the collective prayer for deliverance, these animal spirits began to manifest themselves. There was a cacophony of jungle sounds. Near the front, a man with a lion spirit attempted to charge me, but another man tripped him and he fell to the ground without reaching me. Several other people, both men and women, dug in the ground with their noses like boars. A number of women slithered on their bellies on the ground like snakes. One man rolled like a log all the way up the incline to the entrance.

I was reminded of the word pandemonium, describing a situation in which many demons are let loose simultaneously. It was remarkable that there was no violence. The name of Jesus was continually on the lips of the workers who were assisting. After about an hour the uproar subsided. The supernatural peace that followed led me to believe that most of the people had been set free.

On the fourth day of the conference my theme was the baptism in the Holy Spirit and how to receive it. After I led the people in a prayer, several thousand began to speak in tongues simultaneously. It was awe-inspiring! Then on the final day I taught the people how to exercise the vocal gifts of the Holy Spirit, and led them into the personal exercise of these gifts. The result was a confirmation of the words of Paul in 1 Corinthians 14:31: “For you can all prophesy one by one, that all may learn and all may be encouraged.”

The conference in Zambia was in many ways the culmination of what God had been teaching me. Deliverance is not an end in itself, but one vital stage without which some Christians will never enter into the fullness Jesus intended for them. Since that time in Zambia, I have conducted similar teaching conferences in several other nations, including Russia, Kazakhstan, Turkey and Poland. In each place I have taught people how to recognise and expel demons – and this has always led to a glorious experience of the power and gifts of the Holy Spirit.

Because of the pressure of these public conferences, and also because the Lord has led me to place greater emphasis on my writing ministry, I rarely counsel individuals today. Through the printed word I am able to help many more people than by one-on-one counselling.

In the next chapter, I will share some important personal lessons that I learned from ministering to others.

12

Flesh or Demons?

From the beginning, ever since man turned from God in rebellion, he has been subjected to two main spiritual evils: sin and demons.

The effect of sin is universal and total: “All have sinned and fall short of the glory of God” (Romans 3:23). Sin has defiled the human race as a whole and every area of each personality individually.

The personality thus corrupted by sin is called in the New Testament “our old man” (Romans 6:6) or “the flesh” (Galatians 5:24). The old man describes the rebellious nature each of us has inherited from our first parent, Adam. Adam did not beget any children until he was in a state of rebellion against God. Therefore, in every descendant of Adam there is the nature of a rebel.

The term the flesh does not refer, in this context, to our physical bodies, but to the corrupt nature that is part of the inheritance each of us received at birth. Two different adjectives are used in English translations to describe this corrupt nature: fleshly or carnal. These are merely two different ways of translating the same Greek word.

For practical purposes, these two expressions – the old man and the flesh – may be used interchangeably. Each describes our corrupt, fallen, sinful nature.

The niv, however, has moved away from the original language. It replaces both expressions by our old self and the sinful nature. It could be said that in this respect the niv is more of an explanation than a translation.

With due allowance made, however, for these differences in translation, the truths unfolded in this book apply equally to the old man, the flesh and the sinful nature.

Although the problem of sin is universal, the problem with demons is not. Many members of our fallen human race have come under the power of demons, but not all. There is a close connection, however, between sin and demons. If mankind had never sinned, we would never have been vulnerable to demons.

A biochemist once explained to me, “A human body is attacked regularly by cancerous cells. When that body is healthy, its immune system identifies and attacks the cancerous cells, and they are unable to harm the body. But when the body has been weakened by illness or some kind of emotional shock, the immune system is unable to do its job effectively, and some form of cancer can develop somewhere in the body.”

Immediately I said to myself, That’s just how it is with demons!

Demons continually seek to invade a person, but when the person is healthy spiritually, the spiritual “immune system” within the person identifies and attacks the demons, and they are not able to move in and take control. Any kind of unhealthiness or emotional weakness, on the other hand, makes a person vulnerable to demonic attack.

The Remedy for Each

In the spiritual realm, as in the physical, correct diagnosis is essential. So it is important to know, in confronting our own problems or those of other people, what we are dealing with. Is it the flesh? Or is it demons? The question is of vital importance because the remedies are quite different.

The remedy for the flesh is crucifixion. By Jesus’ sacrificial death on the cross, He cancelled the claim sin has on our fleshly nature. Paul states this as historical fact: “Our old man was crucified with [Jesus]” (Romans 6:6).

But each of us must make a personal application of the cross to our fleshly nature. Paul says, therefore, in Galatians 5:24, “And those who are Christ’s have crucified the flesh with its passions and desires.” Once we have made this personal application of the cross, we can echo Paul’s words in Galatians 2:20: “I have been crucified with Christ; it is no longer I who live, but Christ lives in me. . . .” Crucifixion, then, is the remedy for our fleshly nature. It is a remedy each of us needs to apply personally.

The remedy for demons, on the other hand – as often demonstrated in the ministry of Jesus – is to cast them out.

These two remedies are not interchangeable. It is not possible to cast out the flesh, and it is not possible to crucify a demon.

Looking back over my own struggle with depression, described in chapter 4, I realised that was precisely the mistake I was making. I was trying to apply crucifixion – the remedy for the flesh – while I was actually dealing with a demon, and the remedy was to expel it. As soon as I understood my problem and applied the right remedy, I was delivered.

I have also confronted the problem in reverse when a person tries to apply to the flesh the remedy appropriate only for demons.

A man came to me once and said, “Brother Prince, I want you to cast a demon out of me.”

“How does the demon affect you?” I asked.

“I just can’t get on with my wife,” he replied. “There’s no harmony between us.”

I listened carefully as he described how the disharmony between them affected both their lives. Eventually I said, “I don’t believe you have a demon that needs to be cast out. What you need is to apply the cross to your fleshly nature.”

It was obvious, however, that he was not satisfied. He had viewed deliverance from a demon as a “quick fix” that would substitute for the painful task of crucifying his own flesh.

Crucifixion is the distinguishing mark of those who truly belong to Christ. God is not interested in our church membership or denominational labels. He looks to see if our old, fleshly way of life has come to an end at the foot of the cross. Crucifixion is always painful, but it is the gateway to new life.

The Old Man and the New

Even after the life-transforming application of the cross in our lives, we still have to maintain personal discipline to keep the “old man” in subjection. In Colossians 3:3 Paul says to believers, “For you died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God.” But in verse 5 he says, “Therefore, put to death your members which are on the earth: fornication, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and covetousness, which is idolatry.” We each have the continuing responsibility to keep the “old man” dead.

But even the death of the “old man” is not the final stage in the process. After that occurs, we must “put on the new man which was created according to God, in righteousness and true holiness” (Ephesians 4:24). The sacrifice of Jesus on the cross made possible an exchange. Our “old man” was crucified in Him so that the “new man” might come to life in us.

Just as a completely healthy human body is immune to cancerous cells, so the “new man” in Christ is immune to demonic activity. Most Christians, however, have not yet arrived at this state of complete spiritual health. In my limited personal experience, I have to say I have encountered comparatively few Christians who did not seem vulnerable to demonic activity.

Once again, we may borrow an example from the diagnosis and treatment of cancer. Since most people are not in the state of physical health in which they are immune to cancerous cells, it is necessary for scientists to do research and for doctors to acquire all the information available. This enables them to diagnose the presence of cancer and to prescribe appropriate treatment.

Likewise, there is an urgent need for Christians to learn all we can about the nature and activity of demons. This knowledge is important for all believers, since none of us can claim immunity from the attacks of demons. It is especially important, however, for pastors, evangelists and other Christian workers to whom people look for help. Without this knowledge, as I said in chapter 5, we will often be unable to make a correct diagnosis or to apply the appropriate remedy, and therefore we will not really help people.

Without the probe of discernment, we cannot effectively use the forceps of deliverance. (As I said before, I will offer practical instructions in Part 4 for diagnosing and dealing with demonic activity.)

Now to the third of our seven questions.

16

Do Christians Ever Need Deliverance From Demons?

This sixth question is the one I have been asked more than any other. Often it is asked in an incredulous tone of voice, implying that the answer expected is No!

At one time an official publication of a major denomination classified Don Basham and me as heretics because we were casting demons out of Christians. “What are we supposed to do?” I asked Don. “Leave the demons in them?” The charge against us was based, of course, on the assumption that Christians could never have demons that would need to be cast out. (Later this charge was apparently forgotten, because churches belonging to that denomination have since invited me to minister deliverance.)

In more than thirty years, I have never heard or read a reasoned, scriptural presentation of the doctrinal position that Christians can never need deliverance from demons. Those who believe this, as I said in chapter 5, seem to consider it so obvious that it needs no support from Scripture. But the implications of such a position can be, to say the least, surprising.

A Christian young man told me that Brother Jones, a well-known evangelist, had prayed for him and that he had been delivered from a demon of nicotine.

“I thought Brother Jones doesn’t believe a Christian can have a demon,” I replied.

“You’re right,” the young man answered. “But when Brother Jones prayed for me, he didn’t know I was already a Christian.”

That left me pondering.

In that case, I said to myself, it would seem that unbelievers have an “unfair” advantage over Christians, because they can receive prayer for deliverance from a demon. But once they become Christians, they are no longer eligible!

The term Christian means different things to different people. So before I proceed, I need to clarify my use of the word. I will base my definition on John 1:11-13:

[Jesus] came to His own, and His own did not receive Him. But as many as received Him, to them He gave the right [literally, authority] to become children of God, even to those who believe in His name: who were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.

By Christian I mean someone who has repented of his or her sins and, through personal faith, received Jesus as Saviour and Lord. As a result this person has been born of God – that is, “born again” (see John 3:5-8).

Another way to describe a Christian is someone who has fulfilled the condition for salvation stated by Jesus in Mark 16:15-16:

And He said to them, “Go into all the world and preach the gospel to every creature. He who believes and is baptised will be saved; but he who does not believe will be condemned.”

Such a person has heard and believed the Gospel, been baptised and is therefore saved. Can a person like this subsequently need deliverance from demons?

This depends partly on how the person was brought to salvation or the new birth. In the ministry of Philip in Samaria, the people received manifest deliverance from demons and later believed and were baptised in water (see Acts 8:5-13). It would be reasonable to assume that most of them needed no further deliverance.

Yet even here there is one noteworthy exception. Simon the sorcerer was among those who believed and were baptised. Later, however, when he offered Peter money for the power to impart the Holy Spirit to people, Peter said to him, “Your money perish with you. . . . You have neither part nor portion in this matter, for your heart is not right in the sight of God” (Acts 8:20-21). It would be rash to assume that Simon no longer needed deliverance from demons, even after he believed and was baptised.

Suppose, however, that Philip had followed a different pattern of evangelism – one that is common in our day. Suppose he had preached the Gospel to the people of Samaria and then, without dealing with demons, had invited the people to come forward, say a prayer, sign a decision card or receive instruction from a counsellor. What would have been the result? They would have been saved or born again, but they might still have needed deliverance from the demons that were in them before they became Christians.

I want to emphasise that I am not criticising this kind of evangelism. I have practised it myself. I am merely pointing out that it does not necessarily produce the results that followed the ministry of Philip in Samaria. It leaves open the possibility that the people who respond may still have demons that need to be dealt with. This does not mean they are not Christians. It means that some of them may still need deliverance.

What Happens with the New Birth?

We need to analyse more precisely, therefore, what happens when a person is born again. What is the minimum that happens? And what is the maximum? When people receive “the right [or more literally, as we saw above, authority] to become children of God,” that authority is effective only in the proportion that it is used. A teacher may have authority, but if he does not use it, his pupils will be unruly and disorderly. If a police force does not use its authority, crime will continue unchecked.

So it is with the new birth. Its potential, I believe, is unlimited, but its development depends on the use each believer makes of his or her God-given authority. One person may choose the minimum and simply become a respectable church member. Another may reach for the maximum and become an active, dedicated winner of souls – even a preacher who reaches multitudes or an intercessor who brings many to birth in prayer. The difference lies in the degree to which each uses his or her God-given authority.

One specific form of authority that goes with the new birth is the authority to drive out demons, either from ourselves or from others. When the disciples told Jesus, “Even the demons are subject to us in Your name,” He replied, “Behold, I give you the authority . . . over all the power of the enemy” (Luke 10:17-19). This authority is effective, however, only insofar as we use it. Sometimes demons go out automatically, but usually they have to be driven out.

There are two different sets of circumstances that may confront a Christian with the need to deal with demons:

Demons were already in him before he became a Christian
Demons entered him after he became a Christian

When Demons Are Already in the Person

Let us consider first the case of a person who already has demons when he or she seeks salvation. I have not been able to find any passage of Scripture suggesting that demons will automatically leave at that time. In fact, the ministry of Philip in Samaria suggests the opposite. If the demons left automatically when the people believed and were baptised, why would Philip have spent time and energy driving them out? He could simply have baptised the new believers, which would have eliminated the demons.

Logically, then, if an evangelist does not follow Philip’s pattern of both preaching the Gospel and casting out demons, many will believe and be baptised without being delivered from demons. This could apply to many contemporary Christians.

So, without specific reference to demons, let us consider more generally what happens when a person is born again. The Scripture does not suggest that new Christians are automatically exempt from all the consequences of what happened to them before they became believers. Consider a woman who suffers from chronic sinusitis caused by bacteria. She becomes a Christian but the sinusitis continues. The natural explanation would be that the sinusitis is still caused by the same bacteria. No one would dispute that conclusion on doctrinal grounds.

Now let us consider a man who has severe emotional problems caused by demons. The man becomes a Christian but the problems continue. Is there any scriptural reason to question that his emotional problems are still caused by demons? The child of alcoholic parents, for instance, may have been exposed to demons of anger and fear. If he later becomes a believer but continues to be subject to uncontrollable fits of anger or fear, the obvious explanation is that the demons of anger and fear still need to be driven out.

The same applies to those who have exposed themselves to demons through involvement with drugs, alcohol, sexual immorality or the occult. If, when they become Christians, they are still held in bondage by some of the evil forces to which they exposed themselves previously, the explanation is simple: They need to be delivered from the demons that cause the bondages.

But God be thanked! As Christians we have available the authority of Jesus Himself, and we can deal with all the forms of demonic pressure to which we may have opened ourselves. That authority is not effective, however, until it is exercised in active faith.

The doctrine that Christians are no longer subject to demonic activity can lead to one or the other of two unfortunate results. Either a believer may yield to demonic pressures with some comment like “I can’t help myself; that’s just the way I am.” Or he or she may seek to suppress the pressures within, and in so doing expend much spiritual energy that could have been used for more positive purposes. In either case the practical and scriptural remedy is for such a person to treat demons as demons and to use his or her God-given authority to drive them out.

Having said all that, we must always leave room for God’s sovereignty. My own experience of salvation is a case in point. As I said earlier, I came to the Lord out of a background of Greek philosophy, and had been involved in yoga. During the night that I had a sovereign encounter with Jesus Christ, I was on my back on the floor of my barrackroom for more than an hour. First I sobbed convulsively; then a well of joy sprang up within me and began to flow out in waves of laughter.

Before this experience I could acknowledge Jesus as a great teacher and wonderful example, but not the Son of God. The next morning, however, I knew, without any process of reasoning, that Jesus is the Son of God. Years later, after I had begun to minister deliverance to others, I realised that I had been delivered that night from a demon of yoga, which had kept me from being able to believe in Jesus as the Son of God.

Others have received deliverance from a demon of nicotine or alcohol by praying a simple prayer, without even knowing that demons exist. Again, a child of God-fearing Christian parents may receive salvation at a very young age without ever being exposed to demons.

We have no scriptural basis, however, for assuming that this freedom comes about automatically. Wherever we encounter demons, the scriptural response is to expel them, exercising the authority Christ has given us.

When Demons Enter the Person Later

Now we come to the second question: Can demons enter a person after he or she has become a Christian?

It would be naïve to assume that being born again means we shall never again be subjected to demonic pressure. On the contrary, Satan is more likely to increase his pressures against us when we become Christians, especially if we become a serious threat to his kingdom. This is doubly true of those whose previous way of life kept them in strong bondage to him.

As we consider relevant passages from the New Testament, we need to remind ourselves that all the epistles were addressed specifically to Christians, not to unbelievers. The promises and warnings alike apply to Christians. It would be illogical to claim the promises for ourselves but apply the warnings to unbelievers. Furthermore, we must remind ourselves that we have no right to claim any promise unless we have fulfilled the specific condition attached to it.

There are many warnings to Christians to be on their guard against the attacks of Satan. Peter, speaking specifically to Christians, says:

Be sober, be vigilant; because your adversary the devil walks about like a roaring lion, seeking whom he may devour. Resist him, steadfast in the faith, knowing that the same sufferings are experienced by your brotherhood in the world.

1 Peter 5:8-9

There are two parts to Peter’s admonition. First, we are to be self-controlled and vigilant. Otherwise we will not detect the presence or activities of demons. Second, we are to resist demonic pressures, taking an active stand against them. If we obey these instructions, we shall be victorious. But if we are not self-controlled and vigilant, we will fail to recognise and resist our enemies. Then they will invade us and seek to destroy us. The most serious mistake we can make is to act as if there is no danger.

Certain passages in the New Testament warn us explicitly against exposing ourselves to demons. One tool Satan uses regularly for this purpose is deception. In 1 Timothy 4:1 Paul’s warning is urgent: “Now the Spirit expressly says that in latter times some will depart from the faith, giving heed to deceiving spirits and doctrines of demons.”

Paul speaks here about people who, through yielding to the influence of demons, “depart from the faith.” Obviously they could not depart from the faith unless they had been in the faith. As Christians they had apparently opened themselves up to deceiving demons and consequently turned away from their faith in Christ. Our only safeguard is to be vigilant at all times and to resolutely reject all demonic pressures and deceptions that come against us.

Paul gives a similar urgent warning to the Christians at Corinth – even though some today teach that Christians should be delivered from all fear of deception. Obviously Paul had not received that teaching! Speaking to Christians who were the fruit of his own ministry, he writes, “I fear, lest somehow, as the serpent deceived Eve . . . so your minds may be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ” (2 Corinthians 11:3, emphasis added).

In the next verse Paul warns against any false teacher who may come along: “For if he who comes preaches another Jesus whom we have not preached, or if you receive a different spirit which you have not received, or a different gospel which you have not accepted, you may well put up with it!” (verse 4).

There are three parts to Paul’s warning. First, the deceiver preaches “another Jesus.” Second, those who accept this deceitful message “receive a different spirit” than the one they received previously. And third, they embrace “a different gospel” from the original.

Through Paul’s ministry these Christians had received the Holy Spirit. Therefore, when he spoke of a “different spirit” that they had not received, he was referring to a spirit that was unholy – that is, a deceiving demon.

Here is a clear example of how Christians, who have been born again and received the Holy Spirit, can be tempted into receiving a false spirit – a demon. What would open the door to the demon? Clearly, accepting a message that presents “another Jesus.” This is the root of the problem. Once Christians put their faith in “another Jesus,” they receive a “different spirit” – that is, a demon – and begin to believe a “different gospel.”

It is logical, therefore, to ask whether there are teachers in the Church today who are preaching “another Jesus.” The answer is an emphatic Yes!

There is a “Jesus,” for instance, popular in some South American countries. He is pictured as a Marxist revolutionary, championing the cause of the poor and prepared to organise an armed revolution against the capitalists.

Another “Jesus” is popular in New Age circles. He is an Eastern guru who blends the Gospel message with the esoteric teachings of Hinduism or Buddhism. But the biblical Jesus, who is both the Creator of all things and the Judge of all men, is never presented.

Then there is a “Jesus” who appeals to those with humanistic leanings. He speaks continually about love and forgiveness but makes no mention of either hell or repentance. He represents Jesus only as Saviour and never as Judge, and has no place for the parable about the nobleman closing with the words “But bring here those enemies of mine, who did not want me to reign over them, and slay them before me” (Luke 19:27).

There is also the “Father Christmas” version of Jesus telling people that all they have to do is believe and they will receive everything they ask for, from the best-paying job to an expensive automobile and a house with a swimming pool. But he, too, like the humanistic “Jesus,” never mentions hell and never calls for repentance or holiness.

Tragically, many contemporary Christians are being lured into accepting a false, unbiblical “Jesus” in one or another of these forms. Through accepting “another Jesus,” they are receiving a “different spirit” – that is, a demon. This is not a theoretical, doctrinal issue for abstract discussion. It is a matter of eternal life or death concerning which the true ministers of Christ are obligated to warn God’s people.

Christians are vulnerable to this kind of deception, in part because of a wrong doctrinal emphasis in much contemporary preaching. This places disproportionate stress on certain single, one-time experiences, but never teaches people about the changes they must make in their lifestyles, which alone can validate those experiences.

The Need for Ongoing Obedience

The new birth is a marvellous experience – perhaps the most important that can ever happen in a person’s life. But it is only a birth. Its value lies in the new life to which it is the gateway. Christians who go no further in their experience are like children whose parents continually celebrate their birthdays but do not provide them with the nurture and training they need to become responsible adults.

Other Christians place great emphasis on the baptism in the Holy Spirit but make no room for the ongoing work of the Spirit in their lives. Jesus said that receiving the Spirit would cause “rivers of living water” to flow out of a believer’s life (John 7:38-39). Yet some Christians never get more than a “puddle,” or at best a “pond.” There is no continuing flow of the Spirit in their daily lives.

Again, some Christians place little emphasis on the need for a life of continuing obedience and holiness. Yet Jesus challenged the people of His day with this question: “Why do you call Me ‘Lord, Lord,’ and do not do the things which I say?” (Luke 6:46). To call Jesus “Lord” without obeying Him is hypocrisy and provides no protection from the attacks of Satan.

Some Christians claim they are automatically protected from demonic attack by the blood of Jesus. God does indeed offer us total protection through the blood. But here again, this provision depends on our meeting His conditions.

The apostle Peter tells us we are “elect according to the foreknowledge of God the Father . . . for obedience and sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ” (1 Peter 1:2). An obedient lifestyle is the condition for being protected by the blood of Jesus. His blood is not sprinkled on those who persist in disobedience. This is exemplified by the record of the first Passover in Egypt, when Moses told the Israelites:

“And you shall take a bunch of hyssop, dip it in the blood that is in the basin, and strike the lintel and the two doorposts with the blood that is in the basin. And none of you shall go out of the door of his house until morning.”

Exodus 12:22

The Israelites were protected not because they were Israelites, but because they obeyed God’s instructions concerning the blood, and stayed inside their houses. They were on the right side of the blood. If the firstborn had gone out of their houses, they would have suffered the same fate as the Egyptians.

The same applies to us as Christians. Our protection from Satan does not depend solely on our being Christians, but on our obeying God’s directions. The blood, as I said, does not protect those who continue in disobedience.

The apostle John wonderfully affirms the power of the blood of Jesus to deal with sin in our lives: “But if we walk in the light as He is in the light, we have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus Christ His Son cleanses us from all sin” (1 John 1:7).

There are some important points to notice here. First, the opening word if indicates that there is a condition to be fulfilled. If the condition is not fulfilled, the promised results no longer apply. The condition is if we walk in the light. The two results are we have fellowship with one another and the blood of Jesus Christ . . . cleanses us from all sin.

Second, all the verbs are in the continuing present tense: “If we continually walk . . . we continually have fellowship . . . the blood continually cleanses us. . . .” John is not speaking about a once-for-all experience that never needs to be repeated. The fact that we fulfilled the conditions yesterday is no guarantee that we are fulfilling them today. Just as with the pattern of the Passover, God requires moment-by-moment obedience if we are to claim the protection of the blood.

We need to notice, too, that the first result of walking in the light is that we have fellowship with our fellow believers. If we neglect this, we are no longer walking in the light. And if we are out of the light, then the blood of Jesus is no longer cleansing us. The blood does not cleanse us while we walk in the dark.

Strange as it may seem, the demonic pressures Satan directs against us may actually work for our good. They can serve as reminders of our need to walk before God in moment-by-moment obedience. Perhaps this is one reason God permits them.

A Man Who Loved Jesus

God’s mercy in providing the ministry of deliverance is wonderfully illustrated in the following testimony from a worker in a psychiatric hospital in the U.S.:

One of the most controversial questions within the charismatic move today appears to be whether a Christian can be possessed of a demon. I had only recently received teaching concerning demons and deliverance when I began working in a large state psychiatric hospital. One of my first patients was an intelligent, thirty-year-old man who had spent over ten years of his life in some of the best treatment facilities in the country.

The outward manifestation of his illness was the uncontrollable behaviour of dashing his head against walls and sharp objects, often seriously hurting himself. This behaviour occurred irrespective of treatment or of the man’s frame of mind. The problem became so serious that the patient was fitted with a football helmet, strapped to a bed, and the bed bolted to the floor in the centre of his room.

This young man was a handsome, well-liked person, well-known to the entire hospital staff. The tragedy of his case and what disconcerted me was his love for Jesus Christ. He was a Christian, openly professed Christ, and would weep for joy when we spent time singing, praying and sharing in the Word together. However, for several weeks I was unaware that after I departed from our fellowship, he would go into a rage, calling me profane names and trying desperately to harm himself.

After these reports I feared for his safety and discontinued the visits, relying on God to answer my prayer for his recovery. Yet the fellow became so despondent without my visits that I felt compelled to return. As I opened my Bible to share with him, the Spirit suddenly moved on me to command the demon to leave. Though the words I spoke were almost inaudible, the reaction was immediate.

Never had I witnessed such a gnashing of teeth, screams of profanity against Christ, and evil facial expressions. Not only that, but in spite of being strapped securely to the bed, his body became rigid and rose more than a foot above the bed, suspended in mid-air. The change in the patient was so sudden and violent that I became afraid. I left the room quickly, hoping this would ease his violent reaction.

Several moments passed before I realised the connection between the words I had spoken commanding the demon to leave and the violent display. The Holy Spirit quickened me to return. This time the demonic manifestation did not dismay me. I commanded the demon to leave in the name of Jesus, reminding it of Mark 16:17. Though it continued to manifest, I returned to my office with Christ’s assurance.

From that day forward, this man was completely free of that demon and its violent manifestation. Not only that, but he took his Bible and went throughout the hospital to staff and patients, praising God for his “deliverance from the demon.” Subsequent hospital investigations attested to the miraculous deliverance.

Indeed, it was not my prayers, our fellowship or my sharing the Word that brought restoration in the Christian man’s life, but the casting out of a demon according to Mark 16:17.

18

Characteristic Activities of Demons

Evil spirits or demons are, according to my understanding, the lower echelon of the “spiritual hosts of wickedness” (Ephesians 6:12) that Satan directs against humanity. (See chapter 11.) They have three main purposes assigned to them by Satan: first, to torment and afflict us; second, to keep us from knowing Christ as Saviour; and failing that, third, to keep us from serving Christ effectively.

In accomplishing these purposes, demons are normally invisible. They cannot be perceived by human eyes. We can, however, recognise their presence and activity in the same way that we recognise the presence of the wind. Actually, this is an appropriate comparison because in both Hebrew and Greek, the word for spirit is also the word for wind. We never actually see the wind, but we see the effects the wind produces: dust rising in the streets, clouds sailing across the sky, trees all bending in one direction, rain being driven across our field of vision. All these “signposts” reveal the presence and activity of the wind.

So it is with demons. We do not normally see them, but we recognise their presence by certain characteristic actions. Listed below are some of the most typical of their activities:

Demons entice
Demons harass
Demons torture
Demons compel
Demons enslave
Demons cause addictions
Demons defile
Demons deceive
Demons attack the physical body

Let us look at each of these.

1. Demons Entice

Demons persuade people to do evil. Every one of us has experienced this at some time. Enticement often comes verbally. You pick up a wallet dropped on the street and you see cash inside. Then something whispers to you, Take it! Nobody will ever know. Other people would do the same. If it were your money, they’d take it.

Anything that has a voice is a person, and that voice belongs to a demon that is enticing you. If you yield, Satan will have begun to break down your defences. You will no longer have a clear conscience. You will know you are guilty. That prepares the way for Satan’s next assault.

2. Demons Harass

Demons study you, follow your movements, observe your weak moments, detect your weak places. Then they engineer situations that will open the way for them to slip in.

Take, for example, a businessman who has had a terrible day at the office. Everything has gone wrong. He tripped on the staircase, his secretary spilled coffee on him, the air conditioning failed, an irate customer came in threatening to sue. Then, on the way home, he spent an hour sitting in his car in a traffic jam. When he finally reaches home, supper is not ready and the children are running around screaming. This is when he loses control and starts to shout at his whole family.

He is a kind, gentle man, and his wife and children are shocked. They forgive him quickly when he apologises. His outburst could simply have been a loss of self-control. But the demon of anger was watching, and now it waits for a similar opportunity. When the man loses control again, the demon seizes that unguarded moment and slips in.

Soon his wife notices a change in him. His love for his family has not changed, but there are times when something else takes over. His eyes reveal a strange glint. When the demon of anger gains control, he abuses his family, actually hurting those he loves the most. Afterward he is ashamed and remorseful. He says, “I don’t know what made me do it.”

This is just one of many examples of how demons will harass a person until they can find a place or moment of weakness through which they can gain entrance.

3. Demons Torture

Jesus related the parable of a servant whose master forgave him a debt of several million dollars, but who then refused to forgive a fellow servant a debt of just a few dollars. The parable concludes with a judgement on that unforgiving servant: “And his master was angry, and delivered him to the torturers until he should pay all that was due to him” (Matthew 18:34). In the next verse Jesus applied this parable to all Christians: “So My heavenly Father also will do to you if each of you, from his heart, does not forgive his brother his trespasses.”

The torturers, I believe, are demons. I have encountered hundreds of Christians who are in the hands of the torturers for one simple reason: unforgiveness. They have claimed forgiveness from God for the incalculable debt of all their sins, yet they refuse to forgive another person for some offence, real or imagined.

After Jesus taught His followers the model prayer we have come to call the Lord’s Prayer, He added only one comment:

“For if you forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you. But if you do not forgive men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.”

Matthew 6:14-15

There are various forms of torture to which we may be subjected. There is, for instance, physical torture. One example is arthritis: twisting, torturing, crippling, binding. I am not suggesting that all arthritis has a demonic cause. Yet it is remarkable how often arthritis is actually associated with an inner attitude of resentment, unforgiveness, bitterness. (In chapter 20 I will give a remarkable example of deliverance from arthritis.)

Then there is mental torment. One common form is the fear of going insane. I have been surprised by how many Christians are tortured by this fear. Frequently they are ashamed to confess it to anyone.

Like the enticement to do evil, this demonic attack may also take a verbal form: Your Aunt Lois just entered a mental institution, and your neighbour had a nervous breakdown. And you’ll be next! Usually this fear is the work of accusing demons that continually bombard the person’s mind.

Another form of spiritual torture is an inner accusation that says, You’ve committed the unforgivable sin. When a person tells me he is being assailed by this thought, I always answer, “That’s nothing but an accusation of a lying spirit. If you really had committed the unforgivable sin, you would be so hardened that you wouldn’t care. The fact that you are concerned about it proves that you have not committed it.”

4. Demons Compel

No word is more characteristic of demon activity than the word compulsive. Behind most compulsions is a demon – for example, compulsive smoking and compulsive consumption of alcohol or drugs. It is well established that these activities produce a chemical reaction in the brain. This opens up a place of weakness in a very sensitive area through which demons can easily enter.

Compulsive eating can also be demonic. But gluttony is “respectable.” You may not find many alcoholics in the contemporary Church, but you will find many gluttons! Compulsive eating usually starts with the loss of self-control. Then one day gluttony slips in. Christians are often unwilling to acknowledge that they are compulsive eaters. But acknowledging the sin is the essential first step to deliverance.

Once, at the end of a deliverance service, a woman came to me and confessed that she had a demon of gluttony. When she was delivered, she vomited onto the carpet. She was embarrassed, of course, and everyone was concerned about the carpet. Later I asked myself, Which is more important? To have a clean carpet and a dirty woman? Or a dirty carpet and a clean woman?

There are many other forms of compulsion. One is garrulousness – compulsive talking. There are many warnings against this in Scripture. For instance: “In the multitude of words sin is not lacking. But he who restrains his lips is wise” (Proverbs 10:19). Excessive talking will always end in some form of sin. Again, the apostle James said that if anyone “does not bridle his tongue . . . this one’s religion is useless” (James 1:26). If you have not kept your tongue under control, you may have opened the way for a demon. Two demons that might seize such an opportunity are gossip and criticism. Both are at home in religious circles!

We all need to stop and check on ourselves: Are there things I do simply out of compulsion? We may have become so accustomed to our habits that we are hardly aware of them – yet they may be demonic. After one deliverance service, I received a letter from a woman who said, “For the first time in 25 years, I’ve been a week without biting my nails!”

5. Demons Enslave

Let us take an example from an area that few in church talk about: sex. Suppose you have committed sexual sin. You repent and meet God’s conditions for forgiveness. You know you are not only forgiven but justified – “just-as-if” you had never sinned (see Romans 8:30). But you still have an intense desire to commit the same sin, even though you hate it. You are sure you have been forgiven, but you are not free. You are enslaved.

One very common example is masturbation. Some psychologists say masturbation is normal and healthy. It is not worthwhile to argue about that. I simply know there are thousands of people, both men and women, who masturbate and then hate themselves for doing it. Each time they say, “Never again!” But it happens again. They are enslaved.

In chapter 5 I spoke of Roger, whom Lydia and I failed to help. Years later, while conducting deliverance services in various parts of the world, I often heard people – men and women alike – saying the same kind of things he said: “I can feel it in my fingers. They’re tingling. They’re getting stiff!”

How grateful I am to the Lord that I have learned the answer! Now I tell people in my teaching, “You can be set free from masturbation. Just be determined. Come against it in the name of Jesus. Shake it out of your fingers until you can feel they’re free.”

Over the years I have seen hundreds of people delivered in this way from the tormenting demon of masturbation.

Let me add that marriage does not necessarily resolve the problem of masturbation, as we read in the testimony in chapter 14. If either partner still has a demon of masturbation, the demon will seek to obtain for itself the physical satisfaction that should be enjoyed by the other partner. This is one reason the sexual relationship in some marriages does not provide the physical satisfaction that each partner should expect.

When we combine compel and enslave, we arrive at a particular form of enslavement.

6. Demons Cause Addictions

I have discovered that an addiction is often like a branch growing out of another, larger branch. To help people, we may have to go beneath the addiction and discover the larger branch out of which it grows. Two common examples are continuing personal frustration and a deep emotional need that is not being fulfilled.

Let us take, as an example, two married women, one an Episcopalian and the other from the Church of God. Each is aware that her husband runs after other women, spends money on himself that she needs for housekeeping, and shows little interest in his family. Each is reaching out desperately for some source of comfort.

The Episcopalian walks across her living room to the cocktail cabinet and becomes an alcoholic. The woman from the Church of God, who would never go near an alcoholic beverage, goes to the refrigerator and eats everything in sight. She becomes a foodaholic – a glutton.

In either case, deliverance from the addiction, whether alcohol or food, will probably not be complete unless the branch that supports the addiction – each woman’s frustration with her husband – is dealt with. The best solution would be for the husband to repent and change. But even if he does not, the wife cannot expect to be set free unless she forgives him and lays down all her bitterness or resentment against him.

In the U.S. today more than fifty percent of all households are singles. As a result, the deep emotional need for loving companionship may be left unsatisfied. If a person feels betrayed and cut off by a parent, spouse or friend, he or she may turn instead to a dog or cat or some other pet. (Animals are often more loyal than humans – and also less demanding!) This longing for companionship may result in a strange kind of addiction.

Some years ago Ruth knew a Christian woman in Jerusalem named Joanna who had no living relatives but kept seventeen dogs in her house. She could not see a stray dog without taking it home. Wherever Joanna went, her dogs went, too. Some of them slept in bed with her. She was, in fact, “addicted” to her dogs.

When Joanna was suddenly taken ill and hospitalised, her dogs went crazy. They rushed continually to and fro, barking loudly. Eventually an exasperated neighbour threw some poisoned food to the dogs and they all died. Soon afterward Joanna died, too. She had nothing left to live for.

In other cases we may not become addicted ourselves, but we may be the cause of addiction in another. Busy parents may discover to their dismay that a teenage child has become addicted to one of the many drugs that are so easily available. Too late they discover that their son or daughter has turned to drugs as a substitute for the love and companionship they were too busy to provide.

Almost anything that is both compulsive and enslaving is an addiction, and there is no limit to the forms that addictions may take. In 1 Corinthians 6:12 Paul said, “All things are lawful for me, but all things are not helpful. All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.”

This provides us with a scriptural definition of addiction: A person is addicted when he or she has been brought under the power of anything that is not helpful. I believe that addictions, so defined, are almost always demonic.

In attempting to solve their problems, people sometimes trade one addiction for another. It often happens, for instance, that a person gives up smoking and immediately puts on excessive weight. He or she has traded nicotine for gluttony.

Pornography is a tragic example of an addiction. The man enslaved by pornography finds himself compelled to tune in to those TV channels that satisfy the demon within. He cannot walk past a magazine or video display in a store; it draws him like a magnet. One pastor said to me, “When I travel, the demon wakes me up at two a.m. when the X-rated movies come on. I have to turn it on. I cannot control myself.” His whole body convulsed when the demon came out. But some years later he told me he was completely free.

Television is a largely unrecognised addiction. Some people cannot walk into a room without switching on the TV. It is not a reasoned action. These people may have no idea what they want to watch. They reach for the television set without thinking, just as an alcoholic reaches for a drink. In the long run, the social results of television addiction may be even more disastrous than those of alcoholism.

More recently the World Wide Web is spawning addictions. People have been classified as “addicts” because of social withdrawal and loss of control. Psychologists have discovered that addicts include such varied groups as housewives, construction workers and secretaries. Side effects range from plummeting job performance to broken marriages.

Some forms of addiction have no recognised name. Lydia and I dealt with a young woman once who was a member of a Pentecostal church. She had a compulsive desire to sniff nail polish. “When I walk into the cosmetics department of a store,” she told us, “I’ve got two options. I can either buy nail polish or I can run out of the store. But I’ve got to do one or the other.” When she was delivered, the demon threw her down and came out screaming, just as it did from the man in Mark 1:26.

Another, more familiar addiction is sniffing model glue or a similar product. This is amazingly common among young people, and often not recognised by parents.

Some addictions are more powerful or dangerous than others, but none is beneficial. Two socially acceptable beverages that can become addictive are coffee and soft drinks, especially caffeinated drinks like colas. According to statistics, the average American consumes 50 gallons of soft drinks in a year. Sometimes a person who stops drinking coffee or cola goes through withdrawal symptoms similar to those of a person going off hard drugs.

A decisive factor in the marketing of a commodity is the fact that it can become addictive. Once a person has become addicted, the producer is guaranteed a customer for life. Some tobacco companies in the U.S. acknowledged recently that they deliberately altered the nicotine content of their cigarettes in order to ensure addiction.

7. Demons Defile

That demons defile is not surprising since the Bible calls them “unclean spirits.” One main area that demons defile is our mental lives – our thoughts and imaginations. This can take the form of impure, lustful images or fantasies that project themselves unbidden into our minds. This may happen especially when we are trying to focus on the things of God, either in worship or in Bible reading. Any strong, lustful impulse that rises up in our minds at such moments is almost certainly demonic. Demons oppose our communion with God.

Another area of personality regularly defiled by demons is that of speech. Many men (and women, and even some children) cannot speak three sentences without using obscene or blasphemous language. For five and a half years in the British Army during World War II, I was surrounded by such men. In fact, until the Lord saved me, I was one of them.

That was another element in the powerful, supernatural deliverance I received when I was saved. One day I could not speak without blaspheming and cursing. The next day that language no longer came out of my mouth. This was not the result of an effort of my will. It was just gone! Only later did I realise that God had released me supernaturally from defiling demons. The demons of blasphemy and unclean speech had to go, in the same way that the demon of yoga had gone.

8. Demons Deceive

I believe demons are behind almost every form of spiritual deception. In 1 Timothy 4:1 Paul says, “Now the Spirit expressly says that in latter times some will depart from the faith, giving heed to deceiving spirits and doctrines of demons.”

As I pointed out in chapter 16, people cannot depart from the faith who have never been in it. These are Christians who have been enticed out of sound, biblical faith into some form of doctrinal error. Spiritual deception, I believe, is the greatest single danger that threatens Christians in these latter times. And behind each form of deception is a corresponding demon. Any doctrine that detracts from the holiness of God, or that attacks the person, nature and work of Christ, or that undermines the authority of Scripture, is demonic. (We looked in chapter 16 at the deception of preaching “another Jesus.”)

Already in the first century Jude found it necessary to exhort the Christians of his day “to contend earnestly for the faith which was once for all delivered to the saints” (Jude 3). The need for such earnest contention has increased exponentially since the time of Jude.

Demonic deception, however, goes beyond distortions or aberrations of the Christian faith. It includes all religions, cults or philosophies that set aside any of the great central truths of the Bible, especially anything that concerns Jesus Christ. We need to remember that demons are always trying to conceal or distort who Jesus is.

Another way demonic deception manifests itself is by causing Christians to mimic the behaviour of animals. I call such demons “animal spirits.”

In chapter 9 I described how various animal spirits manifested themselves in our meetings in Zambia. Such manifestations occur in churches in more “civilised” nations, too, and are attributed to the Holy Spirit. By way of illustration, let me quote briefly from a letter I received in June 1996 from a friend who pastors a predominantly white Pentecostal church in South Africa. Describing a movement that had developed in his area, he wrote:

Within a short space of time, a brother emerged out of this movement who, together with his church, led the whole thing into bizarre, unclean behaviour. . . . So, it was not therefore uncommon to hear brethren bark, crawl on the floor like animals and make other related animal noises, all under the power of an uncontrollable force. These phenomena were all attributed to the work of the Holy Spirit.

For instance, in one church men were crawling around on all fours on the ground (like dogs) and lifting their legs against chairs as if in a urinating position. . . In our church a lady arrived one night and began to cackle like a hen at the back of the church. This went on for some time until, in a total frenzy, she jumped up and began to lift her blouse and expose herself. Needless to say, as you can imagine, I have never seen leaders scramble so fast in order to remove the lady from the church.

This account vividly illustrates the power of demonic deception. All the Christians involved in this movement came from churches claiming to believe the Bible. The tragedy is that behaviour of this kind was attributed to the Holy Spirit, who is “the Spirit of holiness” (Romans 1:4). I deal with the question of a counterfeit Holy Spirit in my book Protection from Deception.

9. Demons Attack the Physical Body

In chapter 20 I will trace the connection between demons and physical sickness. Here I will simply mention some other ways demons may affect us physically.

There is, for instance, a demon of tiredness. Some years ago I was involved in a lengthy deliverance session with a woman who, after a while, began to say, “I can’t go on with any more of this. I’m too tired. I can’t take any more!”

I began to feel sorry for her. Then I wondered if it was a demon speaking, not the woman. I challenged it and the demon replied, “That’s right. She’s always tired. She’s tired when she gets up. She’s tired when she goes to bed. She’s too tired to pray, too tired to read her Bible.”

It seemed that this particular demon was acting as a cover for other demons. If it could persuade me to stop, the others would not have to face the authority of the name of Jesus and be expelled. Once I discerned the ruse and drove out the demon of tiredness, then the other demons also came out, one by one.

Another physical effect that demons can produce is unnatural sleepiness. Isaiah speaks about “the spirit of deep sleep” (Isaiah 29:10). Sometimes, when a Christian wants to pray or read his Bible at ten p.m., he is fast asleep by 10:15. Yet the same person can stay up watching TV until the early hours of the morning. Many Christians have testified to being affected by a supernatural force that opposes them when they seek to read the Bible or pray.

Unnatural sleep can also be a means of escaping unpleasant life situations. I knew a woman who sometimes slept as much as sixteen hours at a stretch when she was under pressure at home. When the demon was expelled, it protested, “You can’t cast me out. I’m her salvation!” There was perverted logic in the demon’s words. Sleep was this woman’s way of escaping life’s unpleasant realities. It was a false salvation!

If we go beyond specific symptoms of demonic activity, such as those listed in this chapter, we can discern one general characteristic of most people who are demonized: restlessness. A person who can maintain an attitude of serene composure in all the troubled circumstances of life is probably demon-free. But there are not many such people!

Delivered from a Spirit of Death

The testimony that follows is from an American businessman delivered from a spirit of death:

About three years ago, unbeknownst to me, I entertained the spirit of death. It came to me in the guise of a spiritual happening – i.e., directions from God. Essentially it was impressed on me that I would die before I became sixty, or in about three years, and that I needed to get my life in shape. I had seen a vision of a body in a casket – unrecognisable at first, but gradual recognition came that it was me. The impression became clearer, and I was convinced God was showing me that I would die within three years. So I started doing those things one needs to do to get ready, such as a two-day meeting with my eldest son to give him the “good news”; letters of preparation to others in the family; updating the will.

I commenced to “live to die,” which affects every area of your life. In recent years I have become very familiar with death. Since I became a believer in 1964, I lost my grandparents (old); my wife (age 33) and a son (7) in a tornado; father (68); brother (41); nephew (41); nephew (10) in an automobile accident; six-week-old granddaughter in a premature birth, caused by an accident; and currently I have a granddaughter with cystic fibrosis. Previously my mother died at age 41. In addition my father-in-law died, and my business partner and close friend was killed in 1988 after falling from a ladder. I became so accustomed to dealing with death and its results that I thought God had given me the gifts necessary to be a witness for Him at that critical time.

Starting in early 1987, I withdrew from involvement in much of the spiritual activity around me. I became negative about my business. My health started deteriorating. I had previously had open heart surgery in 1981 and came through with flying colours. But in 1987 the coronary vessels began to close, one after another, so that I had my first angioplasty surgery (the balloon procedure) in November 1987 – my seventh angioplasty procedure in October 1989. On October 18, 1989, I had open heart surgery for the second time. Three of the same vessels involved in the 1981 operation were replaced, along with a new vessel.

Back in the summer, we had signed up for your conference that began on November 19, 1989. Derek, as you began to speak of the spirit of death, spiritual revelation came on me like a slap across the face. As soon as you said spirit of death, I knew immediately whom I had entertained – who had deceived and was deceiving me. I got delivered with severe coughing (quite painful, I might add, due to the recent open heart surgery). I chose to live, not die. I was delivered from the spirit of death – no ifs, ands or buts, right then and there.

In addition, as you began to speak on curses, I became convinced that my familiarity with death was no accident but due to a curse that was being handed down to my children and their children. I met the qualifications and decided to do what it took to break the curse.

Deliverance and breaking the curse over my life were like being resurrected. I was living to die – but now I am living to “live, and declare the works of the Lord” (Psalm 118:17).

19

Areas of Personality Affected by Demons

Whoever has no rule over his own spirit is like a city that is broken down, without walls” (Proverbs 25:28). Solomon is comparing the human personality to a city, the walls of which have all crumbled. A person such as Solomon describes has no inner defences.

The personality of a drug addict, for example, has been so broken down that demons of all kinds can come and go freely. There are no defences left that can keep them out. Such a person needs more than a one-time experience of deliverance. He needs to undergo a process of rehabilitation while his spiritual walls are being rebuilt. This may take months or years.

The analogy of a city may also apply to people not enslaved by drugs. Inside every one of us is something analogous to a major city, with all its different localities and residents. I lived for a while in Chicago, for example, which has many major areas – department stores and fashionable shops; bus and train terminals; banking and commercial institutions. One street was frequented largely by prostitutes and homosexuals. There were also ethnic neighbourhoods whose residents were mainly Polish, Swedish or Jewish. There were also expensive residential areas and slum areas.

Using a city as a pattern, I will briefly outline some of the main areas of human personality, indicating the kinds of demons that take up residence in each area. This, I believe, will help you in your own further study, meditation and prayer.

Emotions and attitudes
The mind
The tongue
Sex
Physical appetites

Then I will devote much of chapter 20 to the ways demons assault the physical body.

1. Emotions and Attitudes

This area of the human personality is assailed by numerous demons, some of which I will mention below. I have come to the conclusion that every negative emotion or attitude opens the way for the corresponding demon. A person who has an outburst of anger or sudden fright is, as I said before, not necessarily under the influence of a demon of anger or fear. But if these emotions become obsessive or habitual, then quite probably there is a demon at work.

Demons tend to operate in gangs. Typically one particular demon is a “door-opener” – that is, it holds the door open for a succession of other demons to follow. One of the most common door-openers is rejection – a sense of being unwanted, unloved, unimportant.

Every human being is born with a deep, innate longing for love and acceptance. When this is absent, the heart suffers an inner wound. I discussed some possible causes in chapter 13. It may be that the mother did not want the baby she was carrying in her womb. Or the parents did not love their child, or perhaps they did not know how to demonstrate their love. Undemonstrated love does not meet a child’s emotional need. Or the sense of rejection may be caused by the break-up of a close relationship – perhaps a divorce. Whatever the cause, a demon of rejection has gained entrance.

There are two different reactions to rejection. One is passive. A person yields to this condition and goes through life with it, but becomes more and more unhappy and withdrawn. The other reaction is aggressive. In this case a person fights back, adopting a don’t-care attitude and developing a shell of outer hardness.

If a person’s reaction to rejection is passive, the “gang” that presses in through this open door includes some or all of the following: self-pity, loneliness, misery, depression, despair and finally suicide. Virtually every suicide, I believe, is motivated by a demon. It is obvious that a demon of suicide does not enter because a person has already killed himself. It comes to drive a person to suicide.

This is usually also true of a demon of murder. It does not come in because a person has already committed murder. Rather, it enters to drive a person to commit murder. Remember that the Bible defines murder primarily as an inner attitude: “Whoever hates his brother is a murderer” (1 John 3:15).

A woman who has had an abortion almost certainly has a demon of murder, even if she did not realise she was taking human life. She probably cannot be set free until she confesses her sin and repents. This is often also true of those who enabled her to abort her child.

On the other hand, if a person’s reaction to rejection is aggressive, it opens the door to a gang that includes anger, hatred, rebellion, witchcraft, violence and finally murder. I have already referred to 1 Samuel 15:23: “Rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft [or divination].” When people open up to rebellion, witchcraft is likely to follow. This is well illustrated by the many young Americans in the 1960s who went into rebellion and, almost without exception, ended in the occult. I thank God that I personally came to know hundreds of these who were gloriously saved and delivered.

For some time I worked with a young man whose life vividly illustrated the result of an aggressive response to rejection. When he was about fifteen, his mother said something that gave him the impression she did not care about him. He went to his room, threw himself on his bed and sobbed convulsively for about half an hour. Then he went to his mother, looked her in the face and said, “I hate you!” After that he began to take drugs, and many demons entered him. He became a leader of a notorious gang in a major U.S. city.

Thank God, that was not the end of the story. When he encountered Jesus, he was wonderfully delivered and transformed. He became a minister and helped many others to be delivered from drugs and demons.

2. The Mind

This is probably the main battlefield of the human personality. Some of the characteristic demons are doubt, unbelief, confusion, forgetfulness, indecision, compromise, humanism and insanity. Usually the people who rely most on their mental abilities are those most open to this kind of demonic attack.

I recall a mild, well-mannered minister of an old-line denomination who came to me for counselling. After we talked I said, “I believe your problem is compromise.” He replied, “Yes, that’s always been my problem.” I said, “It could be a demon.” When we prayed for deliverance, the demon proved to be surprisingly powerful. It actually threw him from one side of my study to the other before it finally came out.

Then there was the Ph.D. candidate from one of the Ivy League universities who came to a conference where I was teaching. Christopher had heard something about my ministry of deliverance, but vowed before the conference that he would leave just the same as he had come. He attended my meetings and observed all that was going on. But true to his vow, he left the same as he came.

While he was in the plane returning to school, however, he experienced such intense pain in his head that he actually thought he was going to die. In his agony he began to pray, and the Lord showed him that it was a demon of doubt. Furthermore, he realised when that demon had entered him. A fellow student, taunting Christopher for being a Christian, had said to him, “Do you really believe Christ fed five thousand people with five loaves and two fishes?” Christopher had replied, “Well, whether Christ really did that or not is not important. It doesn’t affect my faith in Him.” That, he realised, had opened the door to the demon of doubt.

In his agony, Christopher cried out to the Lord for deliverance. Then he felt the demon go out through his left ear. Turning to the woman sitting next to him, a total stranger, he said, “I believe Jesus Christ fed five thousand people with five loaves and two fishes!”

Christopher had stumbled onto a vital spiritual principle: If we have opened the door to a demon by saying the wrong thing, we need to cancel the wrong thing by saying the right thing. Peter denied the Lord three times, but after the resurrection Jesus led Peter to unsay his denial by affirming to the Lord three times that he loved Him (see John 21:15-17).

3. The Tongue

A demon that operates in the area of either the mind or the tongue is a lying spirit. It may speak either to a person’s mind or through a person’s tongue.

As an example of the first, I recall a woman who came to me once for help, complaining, “I’ve been seeking salvation for six months, but I just can’t get saved!” I asked her to tell me which churches she had been attending. When she cited them, I recognised that they all preached a sound, scriptural message of salvation.

Without saying anything to the woman, but under my breath, and in the name of Jesus, I bound the lying spirit that was speaking to her mind, telling her God did not love her and that she could not be saved. Then I led her in a simple prayer for salvation. She came through immediately to an assurance of salvation, which she has never, to my knowledge, lost.

The authority to “bind or loose,” which I exercised in this case, is an important tool in dealing with demons. In Matthew 12:29, speaking about driving demons out of a person, Jesus said, “Or else how can one enter a strong man’s house and plunder his goods, unless he first binds the strong man? And then he will plunder his house.”

If there is a “gang” of demons, the “strong man” is usually the leader, who controls and dominates the rest. In the process of deliverance it will generally be the first to manifest itself.

Further on, in Matthew 18:18, Jesus gave His disciples the authority to “bind” or to “loose” spiritual forces: “Assuredly, I say to you, whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven.”

The authority to bind or loose can be very effective in dealing with demons, but its exercise must be safeguarded by the application of important scriptural principles. (In chapter 25 I outline these principles.)

The lying spirit in the woman I was dealing with was speaking to her mind. On the other hand, a lying spirit may also speak through a person’s tongue. For instance, there are people who are compulsive liars. They are not aware of the lying demon within them, and often they do not even know when they are lying.

Ronald, a Christian businessman, used to visit Lydia and me in our home. As he sat in our living room, his talk would become more and more interesting and more and more improbable. After a while my head would begin to swim. Does he believe what he is saying? I would ask myself. Do I believe it? Yet he was completely sincere, not in the least conscious that he was lying.

Later I discovered how that lying spirit came in. Ronald was the adopted son of wealthy parents who had no other children. They had great expectations for him. If Ronald came home from school with poor grades, his parents displayed their disappointment. So he began to lie about his grades. Eventually he became so used to lying that he did not even know when the lying spirit came in and took over. I later lost contact with Ronald and have no assurance that he was ever delivered.

Compulsive liars are people controlled by lying demons. They deceive others and are themselves deceived. They may even pass a lie detector test.

Other demons in the area of the tongue are exaggeration, gossip, criticism and slander. Exaggeration is a demon that particularly targets evangelists – hence the phrase “evangelastically speaking.” Gossip and criticism are two demons that feel quite at home in church.

4. Sex

Some Christians view sex as inherently impure. They are ashamed even to think about it, much less talk about it frankly. Yet this is not a scriptural attitude. God created Adam and Eve sexual beings, then declared that everything He had created was very good – obviously including sex (see Genesis 1:31).

The sexual urge in human beings is so strong, however, that it is a prime target for Satan. He knows that if he can gain control in this area, he has a powerful tool to influence every other area of behaviour.

I have found that virtually every form of compulsive sexual aberration is the outcome of demonic pressure. This would include masturbation, pornography, fornication, adultery, homosexuality, lesbianism, effeminacy and all sorts of perversions concerning which Paul says, “It is shameful even to speak of those things which are done . . . in secret” (Ephesians 5:12).

There are various ways such demons can gain entrance. I recall a married woman, a Sunday school teacher in a mainline denomination, who confessed to Lydia and me that she had twice been involved in adultery. Yet she was desperately ashamed and apparently contrite. Seeking to discover the source of her compulsion, we learned that her father had been involved in an adulterous relationship at the time she was conceived. It seemed that the demon of adultery from her father had entered her at that moment. When Lydia and I prayed for her on that basis, she received a powerful deliverance.

“Do I need to confess what I’ve done to my husband?” she asked, adding, “He’s a Green Beret4 and always carries a gun.”

“That’s a decision you must make,” I replied. “We cannot make it for you. But I believe God will not fully bless your marriage unless there is complete honesty between you and your husband.”

Later she did confess to him and he forgave her. As a result, she told us that their marriage relationship was better than it had ever been.

The moment of conception is a very decisive moment. (The Chinese calculate a person’s age from this moment.) Children conceived outside of marriage are often born with a spirit of fornication. This pressures them, as they grow up, to commit the same sin.

5. Physical Appetites

This is another area open to demons. The two most basic are eating and drinking, which some Christians see as purely natural, with no spiritual significance. Yet the New Testament depicts these activities as important elements of our Christian lifestyle.

The new believers added to the Church following the day of Pentecost, for example, “ate their food with gladness and simplicity of heart, praising God and having favour with all the people” (Acts 2:46-47). There was something about the way these Christians ate and drank that impressed their unconverted neighbours. Would that be true of contemporary Christians?

Again in 1 Corinthians 10:31 Paul says, “Therefore, whether you eat or drink, or whatever you do, do all to the glory of God.” This raises a very practical question: Is it possible to overeat to the glory of God?

This issue confronts Christians of the Western world in particular, where overeating has become a lifestyle. How many would even consider that they might be enslaved by a demon of gluttony? Yet surely this explains why multitudes switch from diet to diet, never achieving their goal of stable, moderate weight. They are as much in bondage to food, as I said in chapter 18, as others are to alcohol or nicotine. Furthermore, the spiritual and physical consequences of overeating may be no less harmful than those associated with nicotine or alcohol.

Solomon offers a prayer that would be suitable for Christians in bondage to such appetites:

Catch us the foxes,
The little foxes [the little demons] that spoil the vines,
For our vines have tender grapes.

Song of Solomon 2:15

Unimportant though they may seem, these little, fox-like demons may spoil the tender fruits of the Spirit that God looks for in our lives. One form of spiritual fruit that inevitably suffers from the little foxes is the fruit of self-control. It cannot coexist with self-indulgence. We need to remember the warning of Jesus in John 10:10: “The thief does not come except to steal, and to kill, and to destroy.” Demons may come through various appetites or lusts, including alcohol, nicotine or food. But regardless of the door through which they enter, all have the same motivation: to do all the harm they can.

Often the unrecognised barrier to receiving deliverance is pride. It can be difficult for churchgoing Christians to call their problem by its right name and to acknowledge that they need to be delivered from a demon. The woman whose demon of gluttony came out through vomiting was embarrassed. But surely that temporary embarrassment was a small price to pay for deliverance from such a humiliating and destructive bondage.

In addition to these lusts of the flesh, there is also “the lust of the eyes” (see 1 John 2:16). Specific demons enter through the eye gate. One demon already mentioned, which is projected regularly through the media, is pornography. This word is derived from porne – the Greek word for prostitute. Some men commit fornication through their eyes.

Jesus Himself said that this is one way a man can commit adultery: “But I say to you that whoever looks at a woman to lust for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart” (Matthew 5:28). I have been shocked to discover how powerful the influence of pornography is within the professing Church.

There are many other forms of lust, however, that open the door to demons in both men and women. In Titus 3:3 Paul includes himself among those who at one time were “foolish, disobedient, deceived, serving [enslaved by] various lusts and pleasures. . . .” How wonderful is the grace of God that has provided a way of deliverance from these demonic snares!

In the dramatic account that follows, a pastor in Florida describes his experience in dealing with a young homosexual:

“Pastor,” the young man in my office wept, “somebody’s got to help me! I can’t go on any longer.” He bent forward in the large platform chair. “Two years ago I was born again. I really love the Lord, but I still have a powerful lust for other men.”

We waited until he regained his composure.

“Before I was saved, I was a homosexual. Since then I haven’t committed that sin – but the desire is still in me, and I’m afraid I can’t keep it under control much longer. I went to my pastor for deliverance, but he says it’s impossible for a Christian to have a demon of homosexuality, and that I’ll just have to exercise discipline.”

He looked at me with distress gripping his face. “But discipline isn’t the answer! I know there’s a perverse spirit in my body. It is there! Deliverance is the only hope I have. Can you help me?” He began weeping again.

I waited until he had regained his composure. Then I explained, “I wish it were true that Christians were immune to demonic invasion. Unfortunately, our corruptible has not yet ‘put on incorruption,’ and our mortal has not yet ‘put on immortality,’ as it says in 1 Corinthians 15:54. Until that happens, our minds and bodies will still be vulnerable to the enemy. A demon can go anywhere that sin and disease can go. If a Christian can have either of these, he’s also subject to having a demon.”

He listened intently.

“Receiving ministry today obligates you to a series of follow-up appointments in the future. This is not a one-time session. Jesus warned that when the unclean spirit leaves a person, it goes through dry places seeking rest and finds none. Ultimately it will return to the same person and try to gain re-entry. If it succeeds, that person’s final condition will be worse than before. You absolutely must guard against that happening. To prevent it, you have to maintain a life of devotion to God, fellowship with other Spirit-filled believers, and sincerely read your Bible. Doing that will strengthen your relationship with the Lord.”

He agreed.

“I want you to lean back in the chair and listen carefully to what I say,” I went on. “If you comply with God’s terms, you will be set free. The Scripture promises that whoever calls on the name of the Lord will be delivered. That promise cannot fail. God will fulfil His covenant word to you. Just be certain you’re in perfect submission to Him.”

Then I led the young man in a proclamation renouncing every occult, unclean activity in which he had ever been involved. Then he verbally forgave everyone who had ever harmed him, including the men who had abused him sexually in childhood.

“Forgiving them does not mean you agree with what they did,” I explained. “It simply means that through forgiveness you cut the ropes that keep you tied to the injury they brought into your life.

“It’s important that you understand I will be speaking directly to the spirit,” I continued, “and not to you. You must listen carefully, but stay out of the way. Don’t allow the demon’s threats to intimidate you, and don’t protect it.”

He leaned back, eyes closed, as we began.

In a quiet but authoritative voice, I started quoting Scriptures to the spirit. I chose verses reminding it of Satan’s failure and Jesus’ victory. For example: “Inasmuch then as the children have partaken of flesh and blood, [Jesus] Himself likewise shared in the same, that through death He might destroy him who had the power of death, that is, the devil, and release those who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage” (Hebrews 2:14-15).

I reminded the spirit that it was as powerless to hinder the success of this ministry as it had been to stop the resurrection of the Lord Jesus.

“And these signs will follow those who believe,” I told the demon, quoting Mark 16:17, “for Jesus said, ‘In My name they will cast out demons.’” And again, “‘I give you the authority to trample on serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing shall by any means hurt you’” (Luke 10:19).

For about twenty minutes I continued quoting Scripture.

“The weapons of our warfare are not carnal,” I went on, quoting 2 Corinthians 10:4-5, “but mighty in God for pulling down strongholds, casting down arguments and every high thing that exalts itself against the knowledge of God. . . .”

Several times the young man smiled at me with a seductive, sexy grin. Recognising that this was merely a manifestation of the spirit, I continued. Suddenly, when I quoted Romans 16:20, “The God of peace will crush Satan under your feet shortly,” something amazing happened. The young man twisted sideways in the chair, grabbed the arm with both hands and went into a violent, epileptic-like seizure. His body lurched forward in a furious, hammering fashion, vibrating sideways at the same time. I held him around the waist, giving him as much support as I could. It was ugly. Yes, demons are ugly.

The sound coming out of him was equally astonishing. A bellowing noise, like that of a wounded bull, roared from his body. The events of Philip’s preaching in Samaria immediately came to mind: “Unclean spirits, crying with a loud voice, came out of many who were possessed” (Acts 8:7); and Jesus’ delivering the afflicted child when “the spirit cried out, convulsed him greatly, and came out of him” (Mark 9:26).

The seizure lasted several minutes as I continued to rebuke the spirit, commanding it to be quiet and to go. Then, as suddenly as the seizure had begun, the young man collapsed back in the chair, physically and emotionally spent. The room became quiet. The spirit was gone.

Slowly, reverently, as in worship, the youth raised both arms over his head, weeping and laughing, “It’s gone! It’s gone! I felt it go. Praise God, I’m free! It’s gone!”

A moment later he rose from the chair, spending the next half hour walking through the offices, singing, laughing, shouting. “Thank You, Jesus! It’s gone! It’s gone! Thank You, Jesus!”

In that brief period of time, the tormented lifestyle of homosexuality ended. Only its memory would remain.

I had particular reason to rejoice with this young man. For nearly thirty years of traditional ministry, I had been unable to help people with such crushing problems. I had stood by helplessly and watched as church members were torn apart by situations that deliverance ministry could easily have solved. Some of them even died. That failure, common to most of us pastors, radically changed when I received the baptism of the Holy Spirit and learned about deliverance ministry. Thankfully this young man did not become another of my casualties. The truth had set him free.

4. An elite American military commando force.

26

After Deliverance…?

The experience of deliverance in an individual’s life is a wonderful demonstration of the grace and power of God. Sometimes I compare it to the liberation of the people of Israel from their slavery in Egypt.

But the deliverance of Israel from Pharaoh was only the first step in a divine process. God brought Israel out of Egypt that He might bring them into their promised inheritance. So it is with deliverance. It is the first, vital step, but certainly not the ultimate purpose.

There are two important steps that must follow. The process is described briefly in Obadiah 17:

“But on Mount Zion there shall be deliverance,

And there shall be holiness;

The house of Jacob shall possess their possessions.”

Here is God’s ultimate purpose: His people “shall possess their possessions” – that is, their God-given inheritance. He has stated two conditions. The first is negative: deliverance. The second is positive: holiness. Any process that bypasses either of these conditions will not bring God’s people into their inheritance.

There is a logical and practical reason why deliverance from demons must precede holiness. Demons display many different characteristics, but they have one thing in common: All, without exception, are the enemies of true holiness. Until demons have been driven out, neither the Church nor Israel can attain to scriptural standards of holiness.

Let me say clearly that Obadiah 17 applies first and foremost to the nation of Israel. The Church has never replaced Israel. All God’s promises to Israel as a nation will be fulfilled precisely as they were given. (For more on this, see my book The Destiny of Israel and the Church).

There are various places in the New Testament, however, in which the historical experiences of Israel are interpreted as types that also apply to the Church. In 1 Corinthians 10:1-11, for instance, Paul lists a series of experiences through which the people of Israel passed during and after their deliverance from Egypt, and he concludes: “Now all these things happened to them as examples, and they were written for our admonition, on whom the ends of the ages have come.” The experiences of Israel during and after the Exodus, in other words, contain important practical lessons that apply to Christians in the present age.

I believe the same applies to the contemporary restoration of the people of Israel to their scriptural inheritance in the land God gave them. It contains important practical lessons for the Church.

Anyone familiar with history and biblical prophecy can see that the people of Israel were out of their God-given geographical inheritance for nearly two thousand years. But the same applies to the Church. For much of that time we, too, have been out of our spiritual inheritance. If the apostles of the New Testament were to return to earth today, they would have to search a long way to find any church that compares with the one they left behind!

Nevertheless, Scripture encourages us to look forward to “the times of restoration of all things” (Acts 3:21). For both Israel and the Church, the first step to restoration is deliverance. The step that must follow is holiness.

Holiness is the unique mark of the God of the Bible. It should also be the unique mark of His people – both Israel and the Church. In both Old and New Testaments, God says to His people, “Be holy; for I am holy” (Leviticus 11:44; see 1 Peter 1:16).

According to my personal observation – and I have ministered in many different kinds of congregations in more than forty nations over many years – churches today give scarcely any consideration to God’s requirement of holiness. Not only do Christians not achieve holiness; they do not even aim at it!

I compare this to people travelling on tours to many parts of the world. Such tours include visits to a series of different cities or countries. Sometimes the organisers include an “add-on” to the tour package. For an extra payment, the tour can be extended to sites or places not normally visited. I see the contemporary Church treating holiness in the same way. It is an “add-on” for which there is an extra charge. But most people who take the tour are not interested in the add-on.

Yet holiness is not an add-on. It is an essential part of the package of salvation. The writer of Hebrews tells us, “Pursue . . . holiness, without which no one will see the Lord” (Hebrews 12:14). How much salvation do we have if it does not bring us into the presence of the Lord?

If God wills and I live, it is in my heart to write a book to follow this one, the title of which will be Holiness Is Not Optional. Holiness is an integral and essential element of the purpose of God for His people. If God continues to spare my life, I will go on to write a third book, Possessing Our Possessions.

Whether I succeed in writing these two books will depend on the grace and mercy of God. But whether I write them or not, the principle is clearly unfolded in Scripture: Deliverance is only the first step in a process leading to the recovery of holiness and the restoration of the Church to her original simplicity and purity.

Part 4

How to Recognise and Expel Demons

The purpose of this section is to offer practical directions for recognising and dealing with demons. It is not intended to be a complete “how-to” guide, nor is it a set of rules to follow. I do not believe it is possible to devise a guide or set of rules that will meet all the needs. (At least I know I could not do it!)

Rather, in dealing with demons, we need to follow the pattern of Jesus, who said that He “cast out demons by the Spirit of God” (Matthew 12:28). Jesus depended on the Holy Spirit for discernment, direction and power. We can be effective only when we are equally dependent on the same Holy Spirit.

After more than thirty years in this ministry, I still find myself confronted from time to time by situations for which I can find no precedent in my previous experience. My only security lies in consciously and continually acknowledging my dependence on the Holy Spirit. But thank God, He is always dependable!

The material in this section is drawn from two main sources: first, my study of the patterns and examples provided by Scripture; and second, my personal experience in dealing with many demonized people.

In the first two chapters I analyse the main ways demons can affect us and exercise their influence on us. At the end of chapters 18, 19 and 20, you will find personal testimonies of Christians who became involved in dealing with demons. If you follow on through the subsequent chapters, you should arrive at a point at which you can identify demonic activity in your own life or in the lives of others for whom you are concerned. Having identified it, you will be prepared and equipped to take appropriate action.

Finally, a word of caution. Nothing I say in this section should be interpreted as implying that there is no place in our lives for the help we can receive from the medical profession. For my part, I am deeply grateful for the skill and dedication with which doctors and nurses and others have cared for me. Without their help I probably would not be alive today to write this book!